<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">

<article
  xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  version="5.0">

  <articleinfo>

    <title>H2MDK 1.5-3W Fuel Cell Inventor Kit</title>
    <subtitle>User Guide</subtitle>
    <revhistory>
     <revision>
        <revnumber>0.5</revnumber>
        <date>16 April 2012</date>
        <revremark>First draft</revremark>
     </revision>
  </revhistory>
  <publisher><publishername>Arcola Energy</publishername></publisher>
  </articleinfo>


<sect1 id="overview">
<title>System Overview</title>

<para>The H2MDK3 kit enables the user to easily design and build fuel cell systems using one or two Horizon 1.5 PEM fuel cell stacks to deliver 1.5W or 3W respectively.</para>

<para>An open source platform supported by an online developer forum encourages rapid customisation of systems, control and user interface for a wide range of applications from model trains, planes and automobiles, to remote monitoring systems. 
</para>
                                                                   
<para>This manual doesn't attempt to replace the manual that comes with the fuel cell stack. Read the fuel cell manual to get an understanding of how to properly treat the stack.</para>

</sect1>
<sect1 id="features">
<title>Features</title>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>Control system for Horizon fuel cell stack</listitem>
<listitem>Refillable metal hydride hydrogen storage with pressure regulators. </listitem>
<listitem>Complete component kit to build and create your own hydrogen fuel cell power plant</listitem>
<listitem>Development board "shield" for popular Arduino platform with stack control software</listitem>
<listitem>Monitoring and data-logging via USB (voltage &amp; current)</listitem>
<listitem>Open source hardware and software</listitem>
<listitem>Regulated 5V output</listitem>
<listitem>Expansion option to add remote control </listitem>
<listitem>Expansion option to add LCD (Liquid Crystal Display)</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</sect1>
<sect1 id="included">
<title>What is included</title>

       <figure>
         <title>What is included</title>
         <mediaobject>
           <imageobject><imagedata scalefit="1" width="100%" fileref="pics/3w/included.jpg"/></imageobject>
         </mediaobject>
       </figure>

<orderedlist>
<listitem>1.5W stack</listitem>
<listitem>H2MDK Arduino Fuel Cell Shield - all code open source and free to download</listitem>
<listitem>HydroSTIK hydrogen storage. Pre-filled where delivery method allows</listitem>
<listitem>Pressure Regulator</listitem>
<listitem>Silicon tubing (30cm)</listitem>
<listitem>1 x Tube Clip</listitem>
<listitem>1 x Purge valve</listitem>
<listitem>Red/black electrical cable </listitem>
</orderedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="included in the extender module">
<title>Included in the power extender module</title>

       <figure>
         <title>What is included in the extender module</title>
         <mediaobject>
           <imageobject><imagedata scalefit="1" width="100%" fileref="pics/3w/expansionmodule.jpg"/></imageobject>
         </mediaobject>
       </figure>

<orderedlist>
<listitem>1.5W stack</listitem>
<listitem>2 x tee splitter</listitem>
<listitem>Silicon tubing (30cm)</listitem>
</orderedlist>


</sect1>
<sect1 id="what is needed">
<title>What you will need</title>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>Arduino Uno</listitem>
<listitem>USB Cable</listitem>
<listitem>Soldering iron</listitem>
</itemizedlist>


</sect1>
<sect1 id="setup instructions for single stack">
<title>Setup instructions for single stack</title>
<sect2>
<title>Connect H2 regulator and purge valve</title>

<figure>
 <title>Hydrogen plumbing</title>
 <mediaobject>
           <imageobject><imagedata scalefit="1" width="100%" fileref="pics/3w/plumbing.jpg"/></imageobject>
 </mediaobject>
</figure>

<orderedlist>
<listitem>Cut a short length of silicone tube (approx 3cm)</listitem>
<listitem>Push one end of the short length onto the white nozzle of the purge valve</listitem>
<listitem>Push the other end of this tube onto the outlet nozzle of the fuel cell stack</listitem>
<listitem>Cut a longer piece of silicone (about 8cm)</listitem>
<listitem>Thread the longer length of silicone through the plastic tube clip. This clip will be used later to open or close the flow of hydrogen whilst the regulator and HydroSTIK are connected</listitem>
<listitem>Unscrew the nut from the regulator and thread one end of the tube through the nut before pushing the tube onto the regulator and tightening the nut over the tube (there is no need to use a spanner - finger-tight is sufficient)</listitem>
<listitem>Connect the other end to the fuel cell stack inlet by pushing the tube over the inlet nozzle</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Solder wires to fuel cell stack</title>

<important>
Fuel cell stacks must be connected with correct polarity otherwise components will be damaged. 
Please check that the red and black wires are soldered to the correct terminals as outlined below.
</important>

<figure>
 <title>Solder wires to fuel cell</title>
 <mediaobject>
           <imageobject><imagedata scalefit="1" width="60%" fileref="pics/3w/wiringfuelcellsingle.jpg"/></imageobject>
 </mediaobject>
</figure>

<orderedlist>
<listitem>Cut the wires into 15cm lengths: 1 x red. 1 x black.</listitem>
<listitem>Strip approx 5mm of insulation from each end of the loose wires.</listitem>
<listitem>Orientate the stack so that the nozzle is at the top as you look at the side with the solder tags</listitem>
<listitem>Solder one red wire to the left hand solder-tag terminal of the fuel cell stack</listitem>
<listitem>Solder one black wire to the right hand solder-tag terminal of the fuel cell stack</listitem>
</orderedlist>

</sect2>
<sect2><title>Electrical connections to Arduino shield</title>

<figure>
 <title>Electrical connections</title>
 <mediaobject>
           <imageobject><imagedata scalefit="1" width="100%" fileref="pics/3w/wiring.jpg"/></imageobject>
 </mediaobject>
</figure>

<orderedlist>
<listitem>Take the black wire from the fuel cell stack and connect to the terminal on the Arduino shield labelled  GND</listitem>
<listitem>Take the red wire from the fuel cell stack and connect to the terminal on the Arduino shield labelled FC IN</listitem>
<listitem>Connect one wire (doesn't matter which of the two) from the purge valve to the terminal on the Arduino shield labelled PURGE</listitem>
<listitem>Connect the other wire from the purge valve to the terminal on the Arduino shield labelled PURGE</listitem>
</orderedlist>

</sect2>

<xi:include href="h2software.xml" />

<sect2><title>Connect hydroSTIK and load</title>

       <figure>
         <title>Connect hydroSTIK and load</title>
         <mediaobject>
           <imageobject><imagedata scalefit="1" width="100%" fileref="pics/3w/fullsetup.jpg"/></imageobject>
         </mediaobject>
       </figure>


<important>
The fuel cell stack requires unobstructed airflow to all vents in order to function as the oxygen used in the electrochemical reaction is drawn through these vents. Obstructed air supply will reduce the performance and lifetime of your stacks.
</important>

<orderedlist>
<listitem>Ensure the plastic clip on the tube between the regulator and the inlet valve is closed</listitem>
<listitem>Screw a HydroSTIK into the regulator</listitem>
<listitem>Ensure stack is mounted or positioned so that the vents on both sides are open to the air</listitem>
<listitem>Open the clip on the tube to allow hydrogen to flow into the fuel cell stack. It is normal for the HydroSTIK to get cold during operation - how cold will depend on factors including current drawn and ambient temperature</listitem>
<listitem>You can now connect the negative wire of your electrical load to the terminal marked GND and the positive wire to the terminal marked FC OUT</listitem>
<listitem>When you wish to turn off the system, first disconnect your load from the FC OUT terminal</listitem>
<listitem>Close the clip on the hydrogen supply tube to stop the flow of Hydrogen</listitem>
</orderedlist>
                                                  
<para>Care should be taken not to overload the stack. Ensure that the maximum current drawn by your equipment cannot exceed that which the stack can supply (1.5 or 3W). For more information on stack performance, including IV characteristics consult the <ulink url="http://www.horizonfuelcell.com/fuel_cell_stacks.htm">Horizon Fuel Cell H-Series User Guide</ulink></para>


</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="setup instructions for 2 stacks">
<title>Setup instructions using power extender module (2 stacks)</title>

<para>The instructions for using 2 stacks differ only in the hydrogen and electrical connections. These are detailed below. Follow all the other instructions detailed in the single stack setup.</para>

<sect2><title>Connect H2 regulator and purge valve</title>

       <figure>
         <title>Hydrogen Plumbing for 2 stacks</title>
         <mediaobject>
           <imageobject><imagedata scalefit="1" width="100%" fileref="pics/3w/doubleplumbing.jpg"/></imageobject>
         </mediaobject>
       </figure>

<orderedlist>
<listitem>Cut a short length of silicone tube (approx 3cm)</listitem>
<listitem>Push one end of the short length onto the white nozzle of the purge valve</listitem>
<listitem>Push the other end of this tube onto tee splitter</listitem>
<listitem>Cut two 8cm pieces of silicone, connect one to each of the other ends of the first tee splitter</listitem>
<listitem>Connect each free end from the tee piece to the outlet nozzle of each fuel cell stack</listitem>
<listitem>Cut another two 8cm pieces of silicone, connect one to each of the other ends of the second tee splitter</listitem>
<listitem>Connect each free end from the tee piece to the inlet nozzle of each fuel cell stack</listitem>
<listitem>Cut another 8cm piece of silicone and thread through the plastic tube clip</listitem>
<listitem>Unscrew the nut from the regulator and thread one end of the tube through the nut before pushing the tube onto the regulator and tightening the nut over the tube (there is no need to use a spanner - finger-tight is sufficient)</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</sect2>
<sect2><title>Solder wires to fuel cell stack</title>

<important>
Fuel cell stacks must be connected with correct polarity otherwise components will be damaged. 
Please check that the red and black wires are soldered to the correct terminals as outlined below.
</important>

       <figure>
         <title>Solder wires to 2 stacks</title>
         <mediaobject>
           <imageobject><imagedata scalefit="1" width="100%" fileref="pics/3w/wiringfuelcelldouble.jpg"/></imageobject>
         </mediaobject>
       </figure>

<orderedlist>
<listitem>Cut the wires into two 15cm lengths: 1 x red. 1 x black, and 1 x black 5cm length.</listitem>
<listitem>Strip approx 5mm of insulation from each end of the loose wires.</listitem>
<listitem>Orientate the stacks so that the nozzle is at the top as you look at the side with the solder tags</listitem>
<listitem>Solder 15cm red wire to the left hand solder-tag terminal of the left hand fuel cell stack</listitem>
<listitem>Solder 15cm black wire to the right hand solder-tag terminal of the right hand fuel cell stack</listitem>
<listitem>Solder 5cm black wire from the right hand solder-tag of the left fuel cell to the left hand solder-tag of the right fuel cell</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</sect2>

</sect1>

<xi:include href="h2operation3w.xml" />

<xi:include href="h2storage.xml" />

<sect1 id="reconditioning">
<title>Reconditioning</title>
<para>If the fuel cell is not used for several days or is not working at the rated power, it can be reconditioned as follows:</para>

<orderedlist>
<listitem>Remove the purge valve from the stack and disconnect the wires from the Stack Control Shield.</listitem>
<listitem>Fill the syringe with distilled water and connect the syringe to the hydrogen inlet of the stack using a short length of silicone tubing.</listitem>
<listitem>Inject distilled water into the stack until it comes out of the fuel cell from the other nozzle.</listitem>
<listitem>Disconnect the syringe from the silicone tube and connect a Hydrostik using a tube with plastic clip to the hydrogen inlet of the stack.</listitem>
<listitem>Open the plastic clip to allow hydrogen to flow into the stack. You will see the remaining water from inside the stack flow out of the stack. </listitem>
<listitem>When no more water comes out (after about 5-10 seconds), the stack has been rehydrated and emptied and is now ready for the short-circuit procedure which reconditions the fuel cell membrane.</listitem>
<listitem>Take the red and black wires of the stack and hold the exposed ends together, thus short-circuiting the stack for 20 seconds.</listitem>
<listitem>Then open the short-circuit (stop touching the wires together) and close the hydrogen supply clip on the inlet tube.</listitem>
<listitem>Your stack is now reconditioned and ready for use.</listitem>
</orderedlist>
                                                   


</sect1>
<xi:include href="h2supply.xml" />
<xi:include href="h2safety.xml" />
<xi:include href="h2support.xml" />
<xi:include href="h2license.xml" />

</article>
